<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The reasons for which an ecclesiastick of the Romish Church hath left the errors of that communion for to embrace the truth of the Gospel in the reformed religion</title>
            <author>Du Mont, Joseph.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36828</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12260335</idno>
  <idno type="VID">57855</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240977506</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2527</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21498</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12260335</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36828)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57855)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 182:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The reasons for which an ecclesiastick of the Romish Church hath left the errors of that communion for to embrace the truth of the Gospel in the reformed religion</title>
                  <author>Du Mont, Joseph.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Epistle dedicatory "To Mr. Richard Baxter, a most worthy Minister of the word of God" signed: Joseph du Mont.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Conversion.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Anglican converts.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57855:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57855:1"/>
            <p>THE REASONS For which an ECCLESIASTICK OF THE Romish Church Hath left the Errors of that Communion, For to Embrace the TRUTH of the GOSPEL IN THE <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Year 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:57855:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57855:2"/>
            <head>TO Mr. <hi>RICHARD BAXTER,</hi> a most Worthy Minister of the Word of God.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS Good is communicative of it self, I thought my self obliged to make the Publick partaker of the Good I have received from God, by an effect of his Grace, in acknowledging the Reasons which have abliged me to leave the Errors of the <hi>Romish</hi> Communion, that I have fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed all my Life, and preached since I was a Priest thereof, until that God spoke to me, as to <hi>Saul, Why persecutest thou me?</hi> But as I see nothing more able to welcome it into the World, than by dedicating it unto your self, I take the liberty to present it to you, to the end that being sustained upon one of the strongest Pillars of the Reformed Church, it may be better received from it. In effect, what greater advantage could I have in this occasion, where I desire to make known the Errors of the <hi>Romish</hi> Church that I have left, to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the purity of the Gospel, which is practised in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion, than to produce this effect of my Studies, under the protection of a Person, who not only by the force of his Words, in his learned Writings, and by his continual Preaching, but also by the good example of his Manners, maketh known to all the World, that he maketh a particular profession to follow Jesus Christ, in the purity of his Word? In effect, the one appeareth to us in all your actions, and the perfect renunciation of all the Grandeurs of the World, which hath made you so often refuse the eminentest Charges of the Church, doth not permit us to doubt thereof; and the other
<pb facs="tcp:57855:3"/> appeareth in many learned Books, and in daily Sermons, where the force of Grace supplieth the want of Nature, weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by long and painful Studies; so as St. <hi>Basil</hi> said of St. <hi>Gregory,</hi> One knows not which appeareth more in you, whether the holiness of your Manners, or the purity of your Doctrine; you are of those true Pastors who are powerful in works and words, who sustain by their example that which they teach by a lively Word and by Writing; in a word, who made themselves all to all for to gain all to Jesus Christ. Pardon me, Sir, if by advancing these Truths, I do violence to your Modesty: This Consideration hindreth me to say any more of it, and is the reason, why retaining to my self the Sentiments that I am obliged to have of it, I hold my peace, in asking you permission to style my self, as I am, with a most profound Respect,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your most humble,<lb/> and most obedient Servant,<lb/> JOSEPH DU MONT.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57855:3"/>
            <head>PROLOGUE. <hi>Gratia Dei sum id quod sum;</hi> 1 <hi>ad</hi> Cor. <hi>c.</hi> 15. <hi>v.</hi> 10. By the grace of God I am what I am.</head>
            <p>WHen men are conquered by other men, and that the power of Discourse, or the force of Arms, hath constrained them to submit, they own their Defeat, but with difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and diminish as much as they can, the Glory of their Vanquisher: But when Truth hath surmounted, and Grace hath overcome them, they desire that every one should know it, and far from regarding their destruction as a misfortune, they believe all men unhappy that it hath not subjected: So the Apostle St. <hi>Paul</hi> was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shamed of his blindness; on the contrary, he made known to all the World that he had persecuted the Church; and as if his own confession was not sufficient, the holy Ghost hath mentioned in the <hi>Acts of the Apostles,</hi> the scales which fell from his eyes, to the end that he that glorieth <note place="margin">2 Cor 10 17.</note> should glory in the Lord; and that the feeble faculties of man may make known the power of the grace of God, <hi>By the grace of God</hi> (he saith) <hi>I am what I am;</hi> it is that grace which hath made him to acknowledge the Errors of <hi>Judaism,</hi> and to leave the Traditions of his Fathers, for to embrace the truth of the Gospel, and follow Jesus.</p>
            <p>It is the being inspired by this Grace, animated by this Spirit, and moved by these same Sentiments, that I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:57855:4"/> my self obliged to make publickly the same Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, to say with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that <hi>by the grace of God I am what I am;</hi> it is that Grace, which (like the Apostle) hath drawn me (not from the Errors of <hi>Judaism,</hi> but) from the Errors of the <hi>Romish</hi> Church, and hath made me leave the Traditions of my Fathers, for to follow Jesus Christ, in the purity of his Word.</p>
            <p>It is also this Grace, which like this Apostle, hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed me to suffer persecutions, not of those who call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves the enemies of Jesus Christ, as the <hi>Jews,</hi> but of those who are enemies of the purity of his Word, when I would have embraced it, I mean, the <hi>Papists,</hi> who (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more enraged against me, because I left their Errors, than the <hi>Jews</hi> were against St. <hi>Paul,</hi> because he had left their Traditions) have put me (more than once) into an obscure Prison, where I had the honour to suffer the space of many weeks, not only all the miseries, that the hatred which they bear to those who desire to embrace the Religion that I would follow, inspired them against me, but many reproaches, promises, and threatnings, that the most eloquent Doctors of this Communion made me every day, who tormented me more than all the discom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of the straight and infamous Prison where I was detained.</p>
            <p>I can say again with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in <hi>Deep,</hi> and not in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mascus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11 <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3</note> the Governour under the King kept the City of those of <hi>Deep</hi> with a Garrison, desirous to apprehend me; for being escaped from the hands of my Enemies, (for the first time) the King's Lieutenant in the City of <hi>Deep,</hi> (called <hi>De la Boisiere)</hi> (to whom and to many other Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours they had sent my Pourtraicture) stopped and detained me in the more straight Prison of the Castle of <hi>Deep,</hi> from whence at length (like again St. <hi>Paul)</hi> grace hath delivered me, letting my self down by the Wall
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:57855:4"/> through a Window, not in a Basket, as this Apostle, but with a Cord of 40 yards, and escaped his hands.</p>
            <p>It is a truth which hath made so much noise, that not only all that City is informed of it, but almost all <hi>France,</hi> and there are but few <hi>French</hi> Protestants in <hi>London</hi> who do not know it, but particularly the Ministers of the <hi>French</hi> Churches.</p>
            <p>It is that Grace that God hath given me by his mercy, which maketh me say (after the example of the blind man in the Gospel) that Jesus healed my eyes by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of his grace, that I came, that I washed them, and that I have now the use of my sight.</p>
            <p>But as a Patient which is healed of a dangerous Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, must not refuse to tell his Remedy to all those that he seeth in the same danger, particularly when the Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness is spiritual, and there is a doubt of the health of the Soul; since Jesus Christ desireth that we multiply the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents that he hath given us, that he sendeth into utter darkness that bad Servant that had buried his one talent, and that he causeth in our spirits the light of his Truth, but for to enlighten our Brethren with it; I think my self obliged, since that God by his grace hath made me to know the Truth, by curing my Soul of her blindness; I say, I think my self obliged to make known to all the World, the Remedy that healed me.</p>
            <p>I have been long detained by humane Considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which making me know the infallible loss of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Goods, held my Mind in ballance between the fear of the Creatures, and that of the Creator; I saw that in changing my Religion, I made my condition not only less commodious, but it may be miserable in this World, and lost the friendship of many honest Persons, who esteemed me in the <hi>Romish</hi> Church. But at length against all these Considerations that the Flesh and Bloud
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57855:5"/> inspired in me, the grace of God making me consider the shortness of this life, the eternity of the future, in a word, inspiring in me an extreme desire to save my self, hath caused me to seek the way to it. I believed at first, that it was impossible to make sure my Salvation in the <hi>Romish</hi> Church, for the great quantity of Abuses which are committed therein, and that the true way to save ones self, was to have refuge in the <hi>Protestant</hi> Religion, which reformeth them entirely.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Against the Authority of the</hi> Pope.</head>
            <p>ONe of the first Abuses of the <hi>Romish</hi> Church shook me, and that the <hi>Reformed</hi> Church rejecteth, is the great Power and soveraign Authority that the <hi>Pope</hi> attributeth to himself, who calleth himself Successor of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> in quality of chief of the universal Church; he extendeth that power, even to interdict the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms that are in the hands of those which he calleth <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks,</hi> because they do not adhere to his Errors; to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence with the <hi>Christians</hi> to break their Oaths and their Vows, to canonize, and to put (who he pleases) in the rank of the Saints, to give Laws to the universal Church, to remit sins, to draw Souls from Purgatory, to judge soveraignly, and without Appeal, of all the points of Religion, saying, that he cannot err in matter of Faith; he causeth his Foot to be kissed by Kings, his Stirrop to be held by Emperors; in fine, he maketh himself to be adored as the Vicar of Jesus Christ, whom he maketh himself.</p>
            <p>But besides that, St. <hi>Peter</hi> hath never been the Head
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:57855:5"/> of the universal Church; as it is easie to see in his two Epistles, where very far from speaking of Ruling Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority, <note place="margin">1 Epist. c. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. v 3.</note> he saith, that <hi>he is not Lord over God's Heritage;</hi> and that moreover St. <hi>Paul</hi> saying in his 2<hi>d.</hi> Epistle to the <hi>Corinthians, I was not a whit behind the very chiefest</hi>
               <note place="margin">C. 11. v. 5.</note>
               <hi>Apostles,</hi> sheweth enough, that he thought himself not to be subject to St. <hi>Peter.</hi> The same St. <hi>Paul</hi> putteth <note place="margin">To Gal. c. 2. v 9</note> the Apostle St. <hi>James</hi> the first, saying, <hi>James, Cephas and John, who seemed to be pillars:</hi> And again St. <hi>John</hi> in the 1<hi>st.</hi> Chapter of his Gospel, <hi>vers.</hi> 44. putteth <hi>Andrew</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Peter,</hi> saying, <hi>Philip was of Bethsaida, the City of Andrew and Peter.</hi> But when we should be deprived of all these Authorities, that of Jesus Christ is sufficient enough, because he forbiddeth all Ruling Priorities a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst his Apostles over each other, when he saith in St. <hi>Luke, The Kings of the Gentiles exercise Lordship over</hi>
               <note place="margin">C. 22. v. 25 26.</note>
               <hi>them, and they that exercise Authority over them are called Benefactors; but ye shall not be so.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They object, to prove the Supremacy of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> that Jesus Christ said to him, <hi>Feed my Sheep;</hi> but one <note place="margin">St. John c. 21. v. 16.</note> cannot justly infer from thence, that Jesus Christ hath created him Head of the universal Church, because that he did not bid him, <hi>Feed alone,</hi> or <hi>Feed soveraignly my Sheep.</hi> In effect the same Commandment hath been made to all the Pastors, in the 20<hi>th.</hi> of the <hi>Acts,</hi> and 28<hi>th. verse,</hi> where St. <hi>Paul</hi> saith unto them, <hi>Take heed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore unto your selves, and to all the flock, over the which the holy Ghost hath made you Overseers, to feed the Church of God;</hi> and in the 1<hi>st.</hi> Chapter of St. <hi>Peter, Feed the flock of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In regard of that which Jesus promiseth to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> to give him the Keys of Heaven; <hi>And whatsoever thou shalt bind on Earth shall be bound in Heaven, and whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thou shalt loose on Earth shall be loosed in Heaven.</hi> It
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57855:6"/> is easie to see, that Jesus Christ by these words doth not give more Authority to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> than to the other Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, to whom he hath given the same power, saith St. <hi>John, As my Father hath sent me, even so send I you.</hi>
               <note place="margin">C. 20. v 21 22, 23.</note> 22. <hi>And when he had said this, he breathed on them, and saith unto them, Receive ye the holy Ghost.</hi> 23. <hi>Whosesoever sins ye remit, they are remitted unto them, and whosesoever sins ye retain, they are retained.</hi> It is that which St. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> confirmeth very well, saying, <hi>Quod dixit Petro, dixit &amp; caeteris Apostolis;</hi> That which Jesus Christ hath said to <hi>Peter,</hi> he hath said it also to his other Apostles. Is it not the same Truth that <hi>Bernard</hi> teached to the <hi>Pope Eugene,</hi> when he said unto him, <hi>Erras si ut sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam ita &amp; solam à Deo institutam vestram Apostolicam potestatem existims.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But although it was as true as it is false, that Jesus Christ had established St. <hi>Peter</hi> for to be the visible Chief of the universal Church, it would not follow from thence, that all the Bishops of <hi>Rome</hi> were his Successors in his Charge, because we have no word of it in the holy Scripture; and that moreover the Ecclesiastick Histories teach us, that heretofore the people of the City of <hi>Rome</hi> chose their Bishop; from whence it is easie to see, that the Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> was not the Head of the universal Church: For I pray you, who giveth the the power to that people to give a Head to the universal Church, and to establish <hi>Linus</hi> Bishop over the Apostles, who remained after the death of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> as St. <hi>John,</hi> and the others?</p>
            <p>But <hi>(Dato non concesso)</hi> that St. <hi>Peter</hi> was the Chief of all the Church, that he hath made his residence at <hi>Rome,</hi> and that he left his place to the Bishop of this City, (which are meer suppositions.) Who sees not, that the Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> is degraded of that Charge, by compo<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ng himself in it of a contrary fashion to that of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57855:6"/> St. <hi>Peter;</hi> for as Pope <hi>Leo</hi> saith, <hi>One cannot be heir of the power of St.</hi> Peter, <hi>if one is not of his justice.</hi> St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> was the spiritual Pastor of his Troop, and the Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> (whom they call the <hi>Pope)</hi> is become the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Monarch thereof; on the contrary, to say with St. <hi>Peter, I want Gold and Silver,</hi> he is more rich than the most puissant Kings. St. <hi>Peter</hi> never would be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>God,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> the 5<hi>th.</hi> on the contrary, he hindred <hi>Cornelius</hi> to prostrate himself before him. You will tell me, it may be, that I speak of a particular; but who knows not, that every Pope, more proud than <hi>Lucifer,</hi> (who would make himself like to God) extols himself above this eternal Soveraign, dispensing as he doth, with men, to keep the fidelity that they have promised to God by Oaths and Vows? for whosoever dispenseth with a Servant to obey his Master, must be greater than this Master; and so the Pope dispensing with men to obey God, puts himself above God. Every one knows, that the Pope dispenseth not only with Vows and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises that men make to God, but also with that Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that they owe him, seeing that he permitteth one to marry his Neece, and the Sister of his Wife, things that God forbiddeth in the 18<hi>th.</hi> and 20<hi>th.</hi> of <hi>Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will say again to that purpose, That the violation of the Ordinances of the Pope, is much more severely punished than that of the Laws of God: Swear and blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme the holy Name of our God, you shall never be punished for it at <hi>Rome;</hi> but if you say any thing in that City against the Pope, you shall be presently put into the Inquisition: Confess your self there to have lyed, stolen, committed Adultery, done any thing against the Commandment of God, the Priest shall give you an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution for it; but if you confess to have eaten Flesh in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57855:7"/>
               <hi>Lent,</hi> he will not absolve you for it: Why? The Pope hath commanded that they keep <hi>Lent.</hi> But that which I detest most in the power that the Pope attributeth to himself, is the shameful Traffick that he maketh with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences, as we shall see.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Against Indulgences.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe shameful Traffick that the Pope maketh with his Indulgences and Pardons, is so untolerable, that it gave the first ground for the Reformation of the Church. In effect, one must have more Concession for the Indulgences of the Pope, than he doth distribute himself, or than he doth sell to the people who belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth them, to hide their Abuses. Those of the <hi>Romish</hi> Church, who have found the way, not only to live by them, but also to maintain their lusts and their luxury, by the great Revenues which they bring them, say strange things thereof. They give to the Pope unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haustible treasures of Merits, that furnisheth him not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the superabundant Merits of Jesus Christ, but also meritorious Works, and Works of Supererogation, that a great multitude of Saints, which have not sinned much, and suffered much, who by consequence (say they) have endured more pains than their sins do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve. The Supererogation of their meritorious Works, giveth to the Church (say they) unexhaustible treasures of Merits, whereof the Pope disposeth when he pleaseth, and in favour of whom it seemeth good to him; and it is that they call Indulgences and Pardons of the Pope. Though a Soul be plunged in all sorts of sins, it may have,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57855:7"/> by the means of these Pardons, (that they buy with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy money) the liberty to fin without punishment, all the time of his Life. Who doth not see the horror of this Abuse. But let us leave these covetous Doctors, that Interest blindeth, and that God abandons in a reprobate sense.</p>
            <p>Let us see what the others say thereof, who are not so passionate, their Doctrine is more plausible, but it hath not more force: The Indulgences (say they) are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else but a relaxation of Penitence imposed on Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners by the Canons of the Church, in consideration of the Martyrs, and which are not accorded by the Popes, but to those who are truly converted. But if they are truly converted, what need have they of Pardons? when Jesus Christ hath changed a Sinner by the efficacy of his Grace, and that his heart which was of Stone, is become a heart of Flesh, his sins are they not pardoned entirely to him? yes without doubt, seeing that they are not pardoned to him but when he is converted; for God regards not in his anger those which he hath not chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, but those which he hath changed and converted, he doth not impute any crime to them, they are no more the object of his condemning anger: on the contrary, he becometh to them a merciful God, who doth regard only the present estate where he hath placed them, by the merit of the passion of Jesus Christ, which is more then suffiaient (say again the <hi>Romans)</hi> to redeem many Worlds: But if the satisfaction of Jesus Christ, is more then sufficient for to pay the pains which are due for our sins, why will they add the satisfactions of men? why will they say that God takes two payments for one and the same debt, seeing that the first is sufficient enough for to acquit it? Indeed is it not to do an injury to the merits of Jesus Christ, to joyn them to Pilgrimages, to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57855:8"/> Nakedness of Feet, to Abstinence of some Meat, and to other like things, for to make together the total satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction which is due for our sins? It will be better to say with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in the 6th. chapter of the <hi>Galatians,</hi> verse 5. that <hi>every man shall bear his own burden:</hi> For I pray you, who is it who hath put the sufferances of the Saints, in the Treasure of the Pope? and, who is it that can assure us that God will be content with so little Money? No, no, it must without doubt be another pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to satisfie this Creditor; as his debt is infinite, he must have an infinite payment, and by consequence he must have the Merits of God, and not Indulgences foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon the Merits of men: but how the goods Works of men, should be meritorious for the satisfaction of the sins of their Brothers, seeing that they are not for their own sins?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Against the Merit of Good Works.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THose of the <hi>Romish</hi> Church who believe themselves not only to be able to merit the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, by the means of their Works, but also to acquire to themselves higher degrees of Glory in Heaven, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion as their Works are more great and meritorious, for to establish better this belief in the Spirit of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, say that the Reformed Church rejecteth good Works, saying that they are not necessary to Salvation; but their Doctrine is as false as that which they impute to us: It is without doubt a calumny, seeing that the Christian Religion (that they call Reformed, because it is purged from the Errors of the Popish Church) belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57855:8"/> that good Works are necessary to Salvation, that it is the way to come to Heaven, that <hi>Faith without Works is dead,</hi> as saith St. <hi>James;</hi> in fine, that good Works <note place="margin">c. 2. v. 17</note> serve to glorifie God, to edifie the Neighbour, to fortifie Faith, and to conduct us to Eternal Life. It saith well, that good Works do not merit Salvation, that they are not the price of this blessed acquisition, but only the way to arrive there; and so it is a calumny to say, that the Reformed Church rejecteth good Works, saying that they are not necessary to Salvation: but if good Works are the way to Salvation, they do not merit it, as a Doctor of the <hi>Romish</hi> Church saith, they are <hi>via regni non causa regnandi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In effect, for to merit a recompence of any body in commutative Justice, by the means of a good Work, it behoveth that the Work, or the Service that one doth, is not due, for these are no merit to pay his debts: Secondly, it behoveth that one offers of his own; for if one offers any thing which belongeth already to the person to whom one presenteth it, there is no merit: Thirdly, it behoveth that not only the Work that one doth, offendeth not the person for whom one doth it, but moreover that this Work may be profitable to him; for there is no merit to offend any one, nor also to do him any thing that is unprofitable to him: In fine, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoveth that there be proportion between the Work, and the Salary that one desireth to merit. None of these things are found in the good Works of men, therefore they do not then so merit salvation. I prove the <hi>Minor,</hi> and for its first part, (to wit) that the Works that we do for God is due to him, St. <hi>Luke</hi> assureth us of it, saying, <note place="margin">c. 17 v 10</note>
               <hi>When ye shall have done all those things which are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded you, say, we are unprofitable Servants, we have done that which was our duty to do.</hi> Secondly, The Good that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57855:9"/> we do cometh from God, we offer of his Goods and not of our own; <hi>Thine are mine,</hi> saith Jesus Christ in St. <hi>John.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. v 10</note> Thirdly, Not only our good Works do not signifie any thing to him, for he hath not need of our service, it is we that have need of his grace, but moreover they are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, there is always some rest of our humane infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: In fine, what proportion is it between our good Works and the Kingdom of Heaven? there is none with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt; it behoveth for this eternal Good, a merit and a price that may be infinite, as is that of Jesus Christ, and not that of good Works of men. It is therefore that the holy Scripture tells us, that <hi>eternal life is a gift of God,</hi> and not an acquisition by our proper merits; it is so that St. <hi>Paul</hi> saith writing to the <hi>Romans, The wages of sin is death, but the gift of God is eternal life, through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus</hi>
               <note place="margin">c. 6 v. 3.</note>
               <hi>Christ our Lord:</hi> And the same to the <hi>Ephesians, For</hi>
               <note place="margin">c 2. v. 8, 9.</note>
               <hi>by grace are ye saved through faith, and that not of our selves, it is the gift of God, not of works, lest any man should boast: My Goods are nothing unto thee,</hi> saith <hi>David,</hi> speaking to <note place="margin">Psal. 16. 2.</note> God. There is then no merit in the good Works of men, in point of commutative Justice.</p>
            <p>In effect, if there was any, it should be particularly in their sufferings, seeing that St. <hi>Paul</hi> saith, <hi>For our light affliction which is but for a moment, worketh for</hi>
               <note place="margin">To Cor. c. 4. v. 17.</note>
               <hi>us a far more exceeding and eternal weight of glory:</hi> Nevertheless the same Apostle assureth us, writing to the <hi>Romans,</hi> That <hi>the sufferings of this present time, are</hi>
               <note place="margin">c 8 v. 18.</note>
               <hi>not worthy to be compared with the glory which shall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why then (may one tell me) doth God speak so often of Salvation as of a Salary; he saith in the <hi>Revelation, I</hi>
               <note place="margin">c 22 v. 12.</note>
               <hi>come quickly, and my reward is with me;</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Romans, Who will render to every man according to his deeds:</hi> In fine, in St. <hi>Matthew, Rejoyce and be exceeding <note place="margin">c. 5. v 12.</note>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:57855:9"/> glad, for great is your reward in Heaven.</hi> Of all these passa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges the Papists do form this Argument:</p>
            <list type="syllogism">
               <item>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Major. </seg>
                  </label> Where there is recompence, there is merit.</item>
               <item>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Minor. </seg>
                  </label> Jesus Christ promiseth recompence to good Works:</item>
               <item>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Conseq. </seg>
                  </label> Therefore they are meritorious.</item>
            </list>
            <p>But I explain and distinguish the Minor of this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, saying, that there are Recompences properly me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited, and others which are not so merited; the so me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited Recompences are those whereof St. <hi>Paul</hi> speaketh when he saith, writing to the <hi>Romans, Now to him that</hi>
               <note place="margin">c. 4. v. 4.</note>
               <hi>worketh, is the reward not reckoned of grace but of debt:</hi> And it is not of these Recompences whereof Jesus Christ speaketh, because the salvation that he promiseth for to recompence, is a free Reward, and not so merited, which is given us as a Child who receiveth Cloaths from his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for to have either well written, or done some other thing agreeable to his Father who giveth it him, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause his Work by purchase meriteth it, but because it is his dutiful Son. In like manner Jesus Christ giveth us his Kingdom, not because our good Works merit it, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that they be agreeable to him, but because that we are Children of God his Father, and his co-heirs, as <note place="margin">c. 8. v. 17.</note> saith St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the Epistle to the <hi>Romans.</hi> So that those of the Communion of <hi>Rome,</hi> who will buy the Kingdom of God by their proper merits, renounce the Succession of the Children of God, and from heirs desire to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come buyers; but the Kingdom of God is not bought by the merit of Works, God giveth it freely to his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. <hi>Even we have believed in Jesus Christ,</hi> saith St. <note place="margin">c. 2. v. 16.</note>
               <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Galatians, that we might be justified by the faith of Christ, and not by the works of the Law, for by the works of the Law shall no flesh be justified.</hi> And in his 2<hi>d.</hi>
               <note place="margin">c. 1. v 9.</note> Epistle to <hi>Timothy, God hath saved us, and called us with an holy calling, not according to our works, but according
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57855:10"/> to his own purpose and grace which was given us in Jesus Christ before the world began; and if by grace, then it is</hi>
               <note place="margin">c. 11. v. 6.</note>
               <hi>no more of works, otherwise grace is no more grace,</hi> saith the same St. <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the <hi>Romans.</hi> After all these Authorities and these Reasonings, one must be as proud as a Papist for to attribute merit to ones Works.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Against Purgatory.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth never appear more elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, than when she speaketh of its Purgatory: It representeth there to us Souls tormented in a fire of Brimstone, plunged in so great an anguish of mind, in so vehement affliction, and so sensible pains, that they cannot be conceived. It maketh a description thereof as terrible as pityful; and to make the living subsist by the help that it inciteth him to render to the dead, it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteth a thousand divers pains, that these Souls suffer in appearance in those imaginary places, where it repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senteth them to us in these horrible torments, and as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny means for to ease them thereof.</p>
            <p>But I would know where these Doctors (which judge men after that God hath judged them) can find so many Evils and Remedies altogether: They do without doubt as some Gods of the Heathens, who cured but the Evils that they had caused. But for to cure themselves, I pray them to tell me, if Jesus Christ hath fully and perfectly satisfied to the Justice of God his Father, or if he hath satisfied but imperfectly, and in part only; I do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that they confess this last, seeing that they call Jesus Christ their Saviour, and that he is not the Saviour of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57855:10"/> men, but because he hath fully satisfied for them to the Justice of God his Father, by the effusion of his Bloud, with which he hath cleansed us from all sins, saith St. <hi>John,</hi> in the 1<hi>st.</hi> Chapter of his 1<hi>st.</hi> Epistle; and St. <hi>Paul</hi>
               <note place="margin">c. 2. v. 1<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> to the <hi>Colossians</hi> saith, <hi>And you being dead in your sins, and the uncircumcision of your flesh, hath he quickened toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with him, having forgiven you all trespasses.</hi> They must then confess that Jesus Christ hath fully satisfied for the sins of men; but if Jesus Christ hath fully satisfied for our sins, if he hath effectually washed them in his own Bloud, by the means thereof he hath redeemed us: This Redemption is then perfect, and if it is perfect, there remaineth nothing (by consequence) to pay off our Debts. Why then should one imagine a new Expiation, a second Satisfaction, an imaginary Fire, where one pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisheth crimes which are no more, in a word, a Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory which never was, as it is easie to see by the holy Scripture, which doth not only say nothing thereof, but moreover assureth us by a great many places, that the faithful after their death do enjoy rest. <hi>Isaiah</hi> saith, <hi>None considering that the righteous is taken away from the</hi>
               <note place="margin">c. 57. v. 1.</note>
               <hi>evil to come.</hi> We see in the 2<hi>d.</hi> of <hi>Luke,</hi> that the good old man <hi>Simeon</hi> witnesseth, that he had promise to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in peace after he had seen the Messias. St. <hi>Paul</hi> saith in his 2<hi>d.</hi> Epistle to <hi>Timothy, I have fought a good</hi>
               <note place="margin">c. 4. v. 7, 8.</note>
               <hi>fight, I have finished my course, I have kept the faith,</hi> 8. <hi>hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth there is laid up for me a Crown of righteousness.</hi> The Soul of <hi>Lazarus</hi> in the 16<hi>th.</hi> of St. <hi>Luke</hi> is carried in the bosom of <hi>Abraham,</hi> where he is comforted, whilst the wicked rich man is tormented in the flames of Hell; there is no middle, one must go into one or the other. Jesus Christ in the <hi>Revelations</hi> saith to the faithful Soul, <hi>Be</hi>
               <note place="margin">c. 2 v 1<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>thou faithful unto death, and I will give thee a Crown of life.</hi> The same Jesus Christ, did he not give his Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:57855:11"/> to the good Thief, without any need of going into Purgatory? <hi>To day shalt thou be with me in Paradise,</hi> saith <note place="margin">Luke c. 2<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. v. 43.</note> he to him. This last proof would be alone sufficient enough to convince the Papists, if Interest did not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them from being convinced by Reason that there is no Purgatory; seeing that the strongest Reason that they give thereof, is (say they) that there is no Justice, that a man that hath been wicked all his life, and who nevertheless should be converted at his death, went as well to Heaven, as another who should have lived holy all his life; and so that it must be a Purgatory, where this wicked man who is converted at the hour of his death should satisfie, before he go to Heaven, for the sins that he hath committed in his life-time. For besides that the Parable of the Lord of the Gospel, who recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penseth equally all the Workmen of his Vineyard, giving as much to those that came at eleven, as to those that came at six and nine, is much more strong than their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soning, they can say nothing after the example of the good Thief. They must then confess with the Author of the Book called <hi>Hyponosticon,</hi> in St. <hi>Augustine,</hi> that the Church doth not acknowledge a third place, to the end that he which is not with Jesus Christ may be with the Devil; <hi>Tertium locum penitus ignorat Ecclesia, ut pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sit esse cum Diabolo qui non est cum Christo,</hi> saith this Author.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Against the Invocation of Saints.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WE have already seen the abuses that the <hi>Romish</hi> Church committeth upon the Earth, we have
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57855:11"/> seen the Fictions that it maketh us of Hell, but not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with that, it mounteth even to Heaven, where it maketh us to find new Intercessors, to which (by an abuse that I again dislike, and that the Reformed Church rejecteth) it desireth one to make address, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voque them in any necessity; but besides that, we have no commandment in the Holy Scripture of it, as <hi>Coton</hi> the Jesuit confesseth himself, in the first Book of his Institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the first Chapter, <hi>Of the Invocation of Saints:</hi> In regard of the commandment to pray and to invoque the Saints, the Church (saith he) did never teach that there was any: Do we not see that Jesus Christ in his Gospel commandeth us to address our selves to himself, to be eased of our pains? <hi>Come to me</hi> (saith he, in St. <hi>Matthew) all ye that labour, and are heavy laden, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">c. 11. v. 28</note>
               <hi>I will give you rest.</hi> It is then to Jesus Christ, and not to Saints, that we must address our selves; it is to him alone (saith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in his first to <hi>Timothy)</hi> who is the <hi>Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour between God and men:</hi> he assureth us himself in <note place="margin">c. 2. v. 5.</note> St. <hi>John,</hi> that he is <hi>the Way, the Truth, and the Life,</hi> that <note place="margin">c. 14. v. 6.</note>
               <hi>no man cometh to the Father, but by him:</hi> it is in this <hi>belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Son</hi> (saith St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Ephesians)</hi> wherein he <note place="margin">c. 1 v. 6.</note> hath made us acceptable: <hi>If any man sin,</hi> (saith St. <hi>John,</hi> in his first Epistle) <hi>we have an Advocate with the Father, Jesus Christ the righteous:</hi> why then to address one self to his Saints?</p>
            <p>I confess that one must honour them, that we are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to admire their Virtues, to consider them as great men who being in the Flesh, (as the Apostle speaketh) have not fought according to the Flesh; that one must learn their Lives, to the end to imitate them: and if it is permitted to me to mingle a prophane History in so Holy a matter, as the glory of <hi>Miltiades</hi> hinder'd <hi>Themi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stocles</hi> to sleep, it behoveth that the example of their
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57855:12"/> great actions draw us from sleep and idleness, in which we are plunged: but there is a great difference between imitating them, and invoquing them; the Scripture which speaketh of the one, doth not speak of the other: on the contrary, it telleth us that there is but one only Mediatour, but one Advocate, but one Redeemer, who knoweth our miseries by himself, as he cureth them by himself: that the Saints (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> speaketh) are by his Grace all that they are; that they know (as St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> saith) that when God crowneth their Merits, he crowneth but his Graces; and that far to receive the Vows which one offereth them, and the Incense which one presenteth to them, they say with the Angel, in the <hi>Revelation, Remember that I am they companion in service,</hi> and that it is to God alone that it behoveth us to address our selves to: it is not then the Saints that we must in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voque, but Jesus Christ.</p>
            <p>In effect, if we must invoque the Saints, they must know our hearts, to the end to discern sincere prayers from false; and it is that which none can do, the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the heart of man is a secret that God hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served to himself, <hi>God only knoweth the hearts of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men,</hi> saith the Holy Scripture in the second of <hi>Chronicles.</hi> But how should they know the secret <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 6. v. 30.</note> thoughts of men, seeing that the Scripture assureth us, that <hi>neither have they any more a portion for ever in any</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>lesiast. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. v. 6.</note>
               <hi>thing that is done under the Sun:</hi> it was without doubt for this reason that <hi>Elias</hi> told to his disciple <hi>Elisha,</hi> that if he had any thing to ask him, he should have asked it before he was carried up to Heaven; pre-supposing that when he should be there, <hi>Elisha</hi> could no more ask any thing of him. You see then clearly, that one must not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voque the Saints which are in Heaven, elevate Altars, offer Sacrifices to them, nor sing Hymns of Praises to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57855:12"/> their honour, as those of the <hi>Romish</hi> Church do. The first Christians have been so far from this false Worship, that not one saith any thing of it, in the three first Ages of the Church; nevertheless these Ages have seen <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullians, Cyprians, Clements, Arnobes, Origens,</hi> and seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral others, who have all detested this conduct: so that some Heretick, having risen up, who invoqued Angels as their Intercessors towards God, the Council of <hi>La<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicea</hi> condemned them by a Canon that was made on purpose: what would then this Council, and these Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers say now, if they saw abuses that the <hi>Roman</hi> Church doth commit by invoquing the Saints? if they did hear in the prayers of Christians, speaking to them as to God himself, demanding the deliverance of their evils, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to conduct them in the way of Heaven, to blot out their sins, to enlighten them, and to defend them from their Enemies, they thunder without doubt <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema</hi> against this false Worship, or at least they would retrench (as the Reformed Church doth) this abuse of the Church. But let us say something, before we finish, of the abuse which is committed in the Adoration of their Images; it is again an abuse that I dislike, and that the Reformed Church rejecteth, as well as Transubstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation in the pretended Sacrifice of the Mass; but as this last is an abuse, for the clearing thereof one must have a more ample discourse then this of a little Chapter, I reserve my self to speak thereof in a Book that I hope to set forth suddenly, which shall speak only thereof.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:57855:13"/>
            <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Against the Adoration of Images.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath passed from Spiritual Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, to one very material, that is to say, from the Invocation of Saints, to the Worship of their Images: all the World knoweth, that having put Statues and Images upon his Altars, it causeth them to be adored, prayed unto, and offer Incense to them; they kiss them, they kneel before them, it is not an exaggeration; besides that daily experience sheweth it, the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> saith positively these words: <hi>We believe without doubt that Images of Jesus Christ, of the Virgin, of the Angels, and of Saints, must be adored; he must be</hi> Anath<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ma <hi>who doubteth that they must adore them.</hi> The Council of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantinople</hi> saith, <hi>That he who adoreth not the Image of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, let him not see his face in his second coming.</hi> And the Catechism of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> in the page 483. of the Edition of <hi>Lovain,</hi> approveth those that kneeling before the Image of St. <hi>Katherine</hi> (which Saint never was) say <hi>(Our Father)</hi> it is that a multitude of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple do every day, before an infinite number of different Images.</p>
            <p>But not only the people committeth this abuse, the Doctors themselves and the Priests practice it, saying Prayers which are addressed to insensible Images, to which they speak as if they were alive: Thus beginneth the Prayers that they say to the Image that they call commonly <hi>Veronica; God keep thee, O holy face of our Redeemer, imprinted in white Linen; O holy Image and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Figure,</hi> &amp;c. they speak to the Image of the Cross, <hi>Ave
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:57855:13"/> lignum triumphale.</hi> The excess of Idolaters have never been such, they never adored Statues in Statues, as <hi>Celsus</hi> in <hi>Origin</hi> doth very well show.</p>
            <p>It seemeth that it is not necessary to show that the holy Scripture condemneth this Worship, it sufficeth to remember only the second Commandment of God, who saith, in the 5<hi>th</hi> of <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> 8<hi>th.</hi> verse. <hi>Thou shalt not make thee any graven Image, or any Likeness of any thing that is in Heaven above, or in the Earth beneath, or that is in the Waters beneath the Earth; Thou shalt not bow down thy self unto them, nor serve them, for I the Lord thy God am a jealous God, visiting the iniquity of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers upon the Children, unto the third and fourth Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> There needs no more to abolish the worship of Images, but moreover the reproaches that God maketh to <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> for making of Images to himself, are so terrible, that show us enough how much this Idolatry dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaseth him: it was the reason why <hi>Ezechias,</hi> who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended to contradict the Commandment of God broke the Brazen Serpent, although it was the only hope of the People of <hi>Israel:</hi> And the Apostle who reproacheth so vehemently those Idolaters to have changed the glory of an incorruptible God, in the Image of a corruptible Man, doth not show us enough how much God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth this abuse.</p>
            <p>These are the principal Errors that I condemn in the <hi>Romish</hi> Church, God hath given me the grace to leave them, for to embrace the purity of the Gospel in the reformed Religion. And as it is the greatest advantage that can arrive to me in the World, I did believe my self obliged to make you partakers thereof, for the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, and the edification of my Neighbours. I think my self again obliged to render this Witness to the reformed Church, (that God hath done me the grace to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:57855:14"/> embrace) to say, that its Discipline is able to draw all those that have zeal for the ancient Discipline of the Church, and for the truth of its Doctrine; and that one cannot too much admire this government of the learned and wise Pastors, who are the Rule of their Flock, who do not lord over the House of God, who maintain by their examples that which they teach by their words, who instruct indefatigably their Sheep, who nourish them with the holy Word of God, after the manner that the Apostles did teach it, and who applying themselves to the two principal things that God hath left us in the World, (to wit, Prayer and his Word) form the one with the faithful finging the Psalms and Praises of God, and distribute the second with an easie and solid man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, capable not only to nourish them, but also to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them puissantly against all their Enemies, visible and invisible.</p>
            <p>Be not amazed if I am no more what I was, and if I am that which you are; I was heretofore darkness, but now I am light in the Lord; I was heretofore kept in Chains of the <hi>Romish</hi> Church, and now I sing, <hi>The snare is broken, and I am delivered:</hi> In fine, I groaned hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore under the weights of Humane Traditions, and now I am nourished with Divine Truth. Let us rejoyce then, my Brethren, you and I, in the Militant Church, seeing tha<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Triumphant rejoyceth more for a sinner who is converted to the Lord, then for the ninety nine who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>severed: let us rejoyce with this Grace that God hath done me by his mercy, in saying with the Apostle, <hi>Gratia Dei sum id quod sum.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:57855:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>